so let us look now at the overall
performance and reliability of a raid 4
array for reads
we are getting
on average the throughput of n minus 1
disks we can read data from all of the
data disks but the parity disk has no
useful data on it so for reads we don't
use it
this is
significantly improving read performance
because usually we have more than just
two disks in an array so for example
with four disks we are really getting
for each the throughput of three disks
all of the data disks
for writes however the data accesses are
distributed among the data disks however
every write requires the parity disk to
read and then write we need to read the
old parity updated and then write it
back
so we are getting only one half of the
throughput of a single disk because the
parity disk again needs two accesses for
every right
this is a significant disadvantage and
we will see that this is really the
primary reason why we need raid 5. now
let's look at the reliability what is
the mttf of a raid 4 disk again we have
two options
just like raid 1 the first period we get
is while all of the disks are working
the time we have during that period is
on average mttf of the single disk
divided by n because that's how long we
have for the first of n disks to fail
just like raid 1 after this first
failure we did not lose the data yet
and now we have two options
if we do no repair of the failed disk
then now we are operating with n minus
one good disks
if we do no repair of the failed disk
what we get now is at the point of the
first failure we are left with the n
minus 1 disk array and any disk failure
in that array is going to result in data
loss
so if we don't do repair then to this
we add
the expected time until the first
failure among the n minus 1 disks that
we still have
this plus this
if n is let's say 4
is not going to be better than the mttf
of a single disk so you don't want to
even consider using raid 4
unless you're going to do repairs
so pretty much you don't do this because
it's a bad idea you're not getting any
increased reliability what you want to
do is repair the failed disk in which
case the chances of a disk failing
during the repair period
is the mttf of what's left of our array
with raid1 we had one disk left here we
have n minus one disk left so the mttf
for the remaining disks is lower than
for one disk because we are talking
about
the first failure among the end disks so
for example if we have three disks the
first failure among three
is going to happen sooner than the first
failure among just the one disk and then
we divide that with the mean time to
repair so this is the factor with which
we now multiply our this is for how long
we get a rate for to work until we lose
a disk
so overall
the mttf of our raid 4 array is going to
be the mttf of one disk times again the
mttf of one disk
divided by n times n minus one
times the mttr
for the disk
so note that again you know this is very
small compared to this so this
particular ratio is extremely large
the number of disks
is let's say four you don't want to have
too many disks in a raid 4 array if that
is so then what we get is
the mttf of a single disk that is fairly
large multiplied by something that is
usually in the thousands of or more and
divided
by something that is usually something
like you know if it's four disks it's
going to be 12.
so this mttf of raid4 if we repair the
failed disk every time it fails
we get an mttf that is still very very
large